<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Unto his Grace their Majesties High Commissioner and the right honourable the Estates of Parliament information for Alexander Monro of Bear-Crofts.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06366</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing U100E</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R185883</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53981759</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53981759</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180403</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06366)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180403)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2827:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Unto his Grace their Majesties High Commissioner and the right honourable the Estates of Parliament information for Alexander Monro of Bear-Crofts.</title>
                  <author>Monroe, Alexander, fl. 1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monroe, Alexander, fl. 1691.</term>
               <term>Clerks of court --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Courts --  Scotland --  Corrupt practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180403:1"/>
            <head>UNTO HIS GRACE THEIR <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> HIGH COMMISSIONER AND THE RIGHT HONOURABLE THE ESTATES of PARLIAMENT</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Information for ALEXANDER MONRO of BEAR-CROFTS.</head>
               <p>THE ſaid <hi>Alexander Monro,</hi> upon the ſecond day of <hi>November</hi> 1669, purchaſed and Obtained from Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> then Clerk Regiſter, the Office of an Ordinary Clerk of Seſſion, during all the days of his Life unremovable; As the Gift of the ſaid Office herewith produced, more fully bears; By Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue whereof, and conſidering that the ſaid Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe,</hi> was by his Gift Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in Parliament, Expreſly and Fully Impowered, during all the dayes of his Liſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, to Choiſe and Appoint Clerks of Seſſion, one or more, during their Lifetimes, in the expreſs words following, <hi>(Cum plena &amp; abſoluta poteſtate ei durante ſpatio antedicto, eligendi, locandi, &amp; Conſtituendi Clericos, deputatos, &amp; ſubſtitutos, unum ſeu plures in dicto officio durante vit a dictorum deputatorum &amp; ſubſtitutorum, idque ſemper prout ei expedire, vel emolument<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſubditorum noſtrorum in exequendis dictis officiis conducere videbitur.)</hi> And that the ſaid Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> did name to the Parliament ſix Clerks to ſerve in parliament and Seſſion, who were ſworn and admitted, and approven in Parliament and Seffion, and their Rights ratified in Parliament; It is evident that the ſaid <hi>Alexander</hi> had good and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Right to his ſaid place and office, ſo that except upon the account of <hi>Malver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> lawfully found and proven againſt him, he could not poſſibly be removed.</p>
               <p>Yet true it is, That after he had ſerved faithfully in the ſaid office for ſeveral years, and notwithſtanding of his former many ſervices &amp; ſufferings in the wars for the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Family, and his Country: Nevertheleſs upon a letter impetrat from King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond to the Lords of Seſſion, bearing for all other cauſes, that it was his majeſties pleaſure, That there ſhould be only Three Ordinary Clerks of Seſſion, according to the ancient Conſtitution; He was ſummarly upon the 20 of <hi>June</hi> 1676, turned out by the Lords of Seſſion: who did arbitrarly modifie leven Thouſand Merks for his Office to be payed to him by the deceaſt Mr. <hi>John Hay</hi> his Colleague.</p>
               <p>When his Majeſties Letter was read, the ſaid <hi>Alexander Monro</hi> pleaded, that by Ours, and the common Law, the Lords could not warrantably proceed thereupon, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine any thing concerning his office: which was his property: And to which he had as good Right as any man had to his Eſtate. And having offered ſeveral Grounds in Law to clear the ſame, he craved to be heard by his Lawyers: And offered to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go any tryal, as to what ever might concern the diſcharge of his office: And the Vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of all or any whoſe affairs had been at any time amongſt his hands, Whether e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he had <hi>malverſed</hi> or <hi>Exterſed,</hi> or had been defective in his Duty, or had done any thing unworthy of a Clerk of the Seſſion: And he urged further, That ſuch Letters were many times impetrate upon miſrepreſentation; and therefore craved ſome competent time to inform his Majeſty of the nature of his Right, and of his ſervices done to the Royal Family and his Country, at the Engagement 1648: And in <hi>Ireland</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 164<gap reason="illegible: overwritten" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And at <hi>Worceſter</hi> with his Majeſty, (where his Brother <hi>Lievtenant Colonel Monro</hi> was kill'd; and himſelf taken priſoner:) And in the <hi>Highlands</hi> in the years 1653: and 1654: and other Occaſions; Nothing doubting when his Majeſty were rightly enformed, he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180403:2"/>might rather expect a better imployment by his Majeſties Free gift, Then to ſuffer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice in his property &amp; Office, (which he had purchaſed with his own money,) through any thin which might flow from his Majeſties hands. To which it was anſwered, That he might uſe theſe pleadings on his Services, To be one of the three Clerks appointed by his Majeſty. And to that he replyed, That he could not be one of the three without wrong done to others who had undoubted right; And he craved no more but the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able poſſeſſion of his own. Then he was commanded to remove; And when he was gone, Sentence was pronounced, <hi>Removing him from his Office, and appointing his Colleague to pay him</hi> 7000 <hi>Merks.</hi> Which Sentence was never intimat to him in the ordinary way; Nor was he ſuffered to return again, Wherefore he reſolved the next morning to take his place in the Houſe, and being near to go in, he was pulled hack by Force by ſome Friends who told him, he would be ſent into priſon if he attempted it. And though he anſwered, it would be convenient for him to be ſo treated, yet they carried him away Violently.</p>
               <p>Now by what is ſaid above, it is evident that he was caſt out of his Right and Office by Violence compleated againſt him, after all the Reſiſtance he could make.</p>
               <p>Whereby having ever ſince been debarred from his ſaid Office, and Right, and wanting opportunity to apply for redreſs, till the late happie revolution; He did addreſs himſelf by ſupplication to his Grace their Majeſties high Commiſſioner, and Eſtates of Parliament, craving that his caſe a foreſaid might be taken into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and that his Right to his Office, and the illegal and Awful way of his being thruſt therefra, might be declared, and he thereupon reponed, and for that effect; that his caſe might be recommended to the conſideration of the Commiſſion of Parliament, appointed for fines and forefaultures to cognoſce thereupon, after hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of parties; And accordingly the affair having been remitted to the ſaid commiſſion; And the parties having intereſt, being cited to compear, and the ſaid purſuer at the laſt peremptorie dyet, appointed be the ſaid Commiſſion, having compeared with his Procurators, reſumed his lybel: <hi>Viz.</hi> That he had good and undoubted Right to his ſaid Office of Clerkſhip; But was awfully and illegally thruſt therefrom, by <hi>concuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and ſuch force of Authority, in manner foreſaid, as he was not able to reſiſt. And therefore that the ſame might be ſo found and declared, and he thereupon in Juſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned to his ſaid Office and Right.</p>
               <p>Againſt which it was alleaged be the Defenders, <hi>viz.</hi> The Officiating Clerks perſonally preſent, with their Procurators, That 1<hi>mo.</hi> The ſaid Purſuer had never a legal Tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the Clerkſhip; In reſpect, That by an Act of Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 1621. the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Clerks were Reſtricted to Three, and the Purſuer being but One of Sex, was <hi>ſuper numerarie.</hi> And that by the ſaid Act of parliament, no perſon could be joyned to any of the Three Clerks, without the Clerks own conſent: And that no patent in favours of Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe, Anno</hi> 1661, impowering him to name more as one Clerk in one Office, nor any Confirmation in Parliament, of ſuch an Nomination by Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> in favours of the Puriuers Author, could import any Derogation from the ſaid old ſtanding Act of Parliament 1621. 2do. It was alleaged, That as the Purſuer had no Right, ſo could not the way and manner of turning him out of his Clerkſhip by the Kings Letter, and Ordinance of the Lords thereupon, be underſtood an Act of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion, or Aw upon him; In Reſpect that the Kings Letter was founded upon, and related to the ſaid Ancient and Standing Law: And that the Lords did juſtly debarr the ſaid Purſuer as wanting a legal Tittle, and that there was no force uſed againſt him.</p>
               <p>To both which Points, it having been Anſwered be the Purſuer, That as to the Arguments anent his alleaged not having a Right, The ſame were both Calumnious and Irrelivant. Becauſe 1mo. The pretended Act of Patliament 1621, is but a privat Act conceived in favours of the then Incumbents, that no perſon ſhould be joyned to any of them without conſent, and was never a publick Law. 2do. That it is latent to this hour, and never ſo much as mentioned in the Printed Index of unprinted Acts of that Parliament. 3tio. That ever ſince there have nevertheleſs been ſix perſons officiat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing as is nottourly known. 4to. That the very words of the Statute allows of two perſons in each Office, declaring nevertheleſs, the principal Offices and Clerkſhips to be but three which was never contraverted. 5to. That the Defenders in their print confeſſes, that there was no conſent of Incumbents ſo much as required ſince the Year 1630.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180403:2"/>nor can the World demonſtrate any pretended conſent was <hi>adhibit ex neceſſitate,</hi> of the Laws requiring it. 6to. That in <hi>Anno</hi> 1661, when the Purſuers Author was admitted Clerk and joyned in the Office with <hi>Hayſtoun,</hi> there was a total Vacancy, &amp; <hi>Hayſtoun</hi> having been admitted but to a half of the Office, had no farder Intereſt to Obtrud the want of his Conſent to his Colleague, then his Colleague to him. 7mo. That as the pretended Act 1621, was never a publick Law, nor the Rule of eſtabliſhing the Clerkſhips. So in the Year 1661, upon the univerſal Vacancy of the whole Clerkſhips, Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> his patent allowing him to joyn Clerks in Offices, is not only ratified in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the very Nomination of the haile ſix Clerks is Read, Ratified and Aprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in Parliament, whereby the Eſtabliſhment of the Clerkſhips, was of new Conſtitute by the King and Parliament, which no private perſon can Quarrel, becauſe the Clerk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips were all Vacant, and none had any Intereſt; Nor has the publick, or King and Parliament to this hour altered the ſame. But on the contrar, Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> his very Gift is <hi>Per Expreſſum</hi> made the Standart of the Lord <hi>Tarbats</hi> Patent and Gife, from whom the Defenders derive their Right. Likeas, the Act of Parliament 1685, Ratifies the Eſtabliſhment of two Clerks in each Office, and that with reguard to the Condition of the Clerkſhips in time paſt, <hi>Viz: Per Expreſſum,</hi> three Offices, and two perſons in each Office, without the leaſt Inſinuation of ones Conſent to another. 8vo. That <hi>Havſtoun</hi> the perſon whoſe Conſent is wrongouſly pretended to have been neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, did for ſeventeen years Acquieſce and Conſent to the Purſuer and his Authors offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciating, by communicating the benefit of the Office without Control, and never in the leaſt queſtioned the Purſuers Right; ſo that it was <hi>Jus Tertii</hi> for any perſon elſe to Quarrel the Purſuer upon that head. And as the Purſuer was well founded in point of Right, upon the conſiderations aforeſaid, ſo was it alleadged for him, that the Kings impetrate Letter and Method uſed for turning him out by thoſe in Authority were moſt pregnant Acts of Concuſſion, as have fallen out in any caſe, notwithſtanding of what was alleadged in the contrar, upon the pretended Act of Parliament 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>21, as the foundation of the Letter. For 1mo. The Letter was opponed bearing no mention of the pretended Act of Parliament, but <hi>Per Expreſsum,</hi> mentioning his Majeſties own Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. 2do. That the ſaid Act of Parliament 1621, could be no foundation, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Ancient Cuſtome of three Clerks only, becauſe it expreſly Eſtabliſhes three Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and allows of two in each Office, and <hi>de facto,</hi> two have alwayes officiat ever ſince. 3tio. That the Defenders have in both their Print and Pleadings, groſly prevaricat in adducing of grounds for the ſaid pretended cuſtome of three Clerks only. They firſt alleadging on a Statute <hi>Anno</hi> 1594, mentioning three Clerks, which is nottourly in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetude: Then they pretend the Statute 1621, which Eſtabliſhes three Offices, and allows of ſix Clerks, but finding the weakneſs of the ſaid Act 1621, on the account of all that is abovementioned, adduced againſt it, why the ſame could not ſupport the <hi>impetrat</hi> Letter; They at laſt pretend, The King at his pleaſure without the Parliament, might overturn private mens Rights, by ſuppreſſing the Offices, and places they hold, and bought from Subjects according to the eſtabliſhment of both King and Parliament. By all which it might be evident, the Kings Letter was but impetrat, contrarie to Law, and that the Defenders were but <hi>Ex poſt facto,</hi> excogitating grounds to ſupport the ſame. 4to. That the Lords of Seſſion did moſt unwarrantably proceed in debaring the purſuer ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marly without either lybell or accuſation, for <hi>Eſto,</hi> the pretended act of Parliament 1621, had been a ſtanding Law, and in force, yet the preciſe point that the purſuers caſe differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in from the ſaid pretended Act, being only the alledged want of <hi>Hayſtouns</hi> conſent, <hi>Hayſtoun</hi> whoſe alone intreſt, that point was, ought to have been the only quarreller of the purſuers Right in a legal way, That ſo the purſuer might have occaſion upon the grounds above mentioned, to aſſert his own Right, as abſolutely good and that <hi>Hayſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touns</hi> 17 years acquieſcence, and communicating the emoluments, did preclude all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of the want of his conſent. Beſide, that by the tenor of <hi>Hayſtouns</hi> own verie Right, he had intreſt but in the half of the office, and the purſuer and his author, the other half, ſo that there is nothing more manifeſt than the iniquity done to the purſuer, in turning him out for want of <hi>Hayſtouns</hi> unneceſſary conſent. 5to. As to the matter of force and violence upon the purſuers inclinations, he leaves to the World to judge whither the Lords their baffling all his expoſtulations at reading of the Kings Letter, their ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar debarring of him without giving a cauſe, &amp; actual inſtalling an other in his place, Their arbitrarly modifving of ſeven thouſand merks <hi>Scots,</hi> which was little over a Years purchaſe, of his Office, and that all this was done by authority, and theſe in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180403:3"/>the Government warranted thereto, by the Kings Letter, were not more nor ſufficient grounds to Over-Aw, any man that had the leaſt reguard for his own ſaftie to an awful yeelding to the authority, that injoyned theſe things, eſpecially when the reclaiming againſt the Lords ordinary ſentences in thoſe dayes, was ſo highly diſpleaſing, that the impunging of the Kings pleaſure in his Letter would certainly have a riſen to an, higher crime, as is evident by the very tenor of the ſaid letter, expreſly threatening his Majeſties diſpleaſure againſt the impu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gers of the Lords their proceedings, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if any that ſerved before their Lordſhips ſhould adventure upon it; and likewayes by what the defenders, and the Viſcount of <hi>Tarbet</hi> in their Prints, did at this very time threaten the purſuer with, on the account of this very action; Which albeit the claim of Right does expreſly authorize, and that the Parliament has ſuſtained the ſame upon the grounds pleaded by the purſuer, yet he is threatned to be Arraigned as one guilty of high crimes; 6to. That there was nothing clearer from the points of Law, opinion of Doctors, the practice of Nations and the very cuſtomes and Laws of <hi>Scotland,</hi> then that Subjects may be overawed and concuſſed by thoſe in Authority, and that even by the King himſelf, and for verefying whereof, did adduce whole Schools of renouned Lawyers of great credit in all Chriſtian Courts. And particularly adduced, not only the caſe of the lady <hi>Graves</hi> concuſſion by <hi>Lauderdail,</hi> but likewayes the concuſſion of the Earl of <hi>Mortoun</hi> by K Ja: 5th. The concuſſion of <hi>Bramford</hi> by the then Government, and the concuſſion of all theſe who in the late Government tranſacted for their Eſtates, liferents or joynturs, who were all of them reſtored againſt the Tranſactions and deeds they were over awed into, ſo that as the Purſuer had an undoubted Right, it is moſt palpable, he was turned out of the ſame by concuſſion, and againſt which albeit it be notarly known he did violently reclaime, yet <hi>ex ſuperabundante,</hi> he has ſufficiently proven the ſame by ſeverals of the then Lords of Seſſion, and other Gentlemen beyond exception, ſo that his accepting of the 7000 <hi>m:</hi> can never be ſuſtained in Law as an act of homologation or freedome of election and will in the ſaid purſuer. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions interloquitor upon the ſaid debate, was in the expreſs termes following, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Edinburgh 5. December 1690. The Commiſion appointed for fines and forfaulturs, after full and deliberate adviſing of the above mentioned debate, are of opinion, that the purſuer had a legall Tittle to his office, And was put from the ſame by concuſſion, Reſerving to the defenders to be heard upon the Acts of the purſuers alleadged Homologation.</q>
               <p>Therafter the cauſe being again called upon the 9. of <hi>March</hi> 1691, the Defenders ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the grounds following for inferring an homologation by the purſuer of the Lords proceedings, upon the Kings letter againſt him. <hi>viz.</hi> 1mo. That he acquieſced without any Reclaiming. 2do. That he accepted of the 7000 merks modified, and gave a diſcharge thereof, and renounced the office, and that neither law nor practice, can be abduced for derogating any thing from the ſufficiencie of the forſaid Acts of homologation, So that <hi>Eſto,</hi> the purſuer had been concuſſed, the ſaids Acts of homologation, utterly debarrs him from reſtitution. 3tio. The purſuer did exerce an other imployment, of an advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat which is inconſiſtent with that of being a Clerk.</p>
               <p>It was anſwered for the purſuer. 1mo. That he oppones the Teſtimonies of ſeverals of the Lords of Seſſion, Clerks, and others upon his poſitive and axpreſs Reciaiming both the time of turning him out, and ever ſince. 2do: That the turning the Purfuer out of his Office, the way and manner proven, being an Act of manifeſt <hi>Goncuſſion,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the principles of Law, and the practice of This and other Nations, And that the Lords of the Commiſſion has now found the ſame to have been an act of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion. It is an other conſequential principle therefrom, that ſo long as the cauſe of concuſſion, and aw that was upon the purſuer, the time of his being turned out did laſt, that what ever he did <hi>medio tempore</hi> in purſuance of, or complyance with what was abſolutly enjoyned and commanded, can import no act of homologation, as being in Law no more but the effect of the ſame original Aw, and an act of neceſſity and not of free election &amp; choice, as is notarly held by the whole world of forraign Lawyers; And as the famous <hi>Maſcard</hi> who cites the opinion of the Lawyers, in the caſe of the Biſhop of <hi>Placentium</hi> his being <hi>metu regio,</hi> turned out of his Biſhoprick, for that of <hi>Oſtia</hi> ſhews, That albeit he had not only renounced that of <hi>Placentium,</hi> but likeways poſſeſed <hi>Oſtea,</hi> for five years, yet after the Emperours death, he is reponed againſt his ſaid renounci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation upon the above mentioned ground, expreſly; <hi>Viz.</hi> That during the Emperours
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180403:3"/>life, who commanded him out of his benefice <hi>Durabat cauſa metus;</hi> So that his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounciation, and all that he did in complyance with the Emperors command, was the effect of his dread and aw of the Emperour. So likewayes, is it practiſed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the learned <hi>Durie</hi> in his deceſions 27 <hi>June</hi> 1632. <hi>Gaſſie</hi> againſt <hi>Fleeming,</hi> where a wife is reſtored againſt her conſenting to her husbands alienation of her joyntur lands, becauſe that ſhe having proven that her Husband had overawed her ſome time before, and was yet on life, the time of her conſenting, (for the ground debated, was that during her Husbands life, <hi>Durabat &amp; ſubſiſtebat eadem cauſa metus:</hi>) Likeas upon the 21 <hi>Jully</hi> the ſaid year; The Lords declare in the paraleal caſe that they will decide the ſame as they did the former caſe of <hi>Caſſie &amp; Fleeming;</hi> Thereby eſtabliſhing it as a principle, that while the cauſe and motive of Aw and Fear con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues the aw it ſelf and dread alwayes laſts; And upon which, eſtabliſhed and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traverted principles in Law and Reaſon, it is that by the claim of Right and act of Parliament reſcinding Fines and forfaulturs, the Leiges are reſtord againſt whatever tranſactions they made in reference to the ſaids Fines and forefaulturs, during the late Government, as accordingly the Commiſſion has decided already in the caſe of <hi>Humer</hi> his accepting of a new Tack from the Lord <hi>Yeſter:</hi> That it could not prejudge him of the benefite of his former ſtanding tack. And therefore the purſuer his accepting &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging of the 7000 Merks, &amp; renouncing the office in favours of <hi>Hayſtoun,</hi> who by the Lords arbitration was wrongouſly thruſt upon the purſuers Right, can be no act of Homologation, no more than the Lady <hi>Gray,</hi> her giving a diſpoſition of her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate for a Summ of money to <hi>Lauderdail,</hi> after ſhe was thruſt out of the poſſeſſion. And it is well known, that notwithſtanding thereof ſhe was reſtored againſt the ſame. 3tio. It is nonſence to pretend that the purſuer exerceing as an Advocat, after his being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred, was a Homologation of his debarring becauſe the Officiating as an Advocat is inconſiſtent with the office of a Clerk; For it is obvious that the purſuer, his being altogether idle is as inconſiſtant with the ſtation of an Officiating Clerk, But this merits no anſwer, And it is not true.</p>
               <p>Replyed for the Defenders. 1mo. That the caſe of a wifes being overawed by her Husband, obſerved by <hi>Durie,</hi> has no Annallogie with the Purſuers caſe, that being <hi>ex capite metus,</hi> and the purſuers caſe upon the head of <hi>concuſſion.</hi> 2do. That the ground of the Purſuers pretended Aw and Fear in this caſe, being the Lords of Seſſions ſentence, turning him out, It is uncontraverted. That if any of the Liedges comply with the Lords of Seſſions ſentence or decreet, in any caſe by payment making conform, or giving Obedience thereto; Yea by the very extracting of the decreet, the ſame is ſo farr a Homologation of the ſentence, that the partie cannot be heard to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim. 3tio. That in this caſe there was no Legal <hi>Compuſitor</hi> at all, competent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the purſuer, for cauſing him accept of the 7000. merks, ſo that his acceptance thereof, and giving renounciation, were voluntarie and ſpontaneous deeds.</p>
               <p>Duplied for the Purſuer; to the firſt, That it was an abſurd miſtake in point of Law, To ſuppoſe a diſtinction or difference betwixt the acts of Homologation of a <hi>factum meticuleſum ex metu maritali,</hi> and a <hi>factum meticuloſum ex concuſſione,</hi> for <hi>metus</hi> is alwayes the <hi>medium</hi> in both caſes, only that in <hi>concuſſion,</hi> the <hi>metus</hi> is inferred by a perſon in publick Authority. And in the other caſe by a perſon uſurping, or too far extending a private Authority, and the indureance of the Fear, is in both caſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurate by the continuance and laſting of the cauſe and motive of it. And as to deeds of Homologation and nature of the action of Reſtitution ariſing to the partie Laeſed in either caſes, The principles in Law are indiviſibly the ſame, as appears by what is learnedy Debated, by <hi>Durie</hi> from the Texts in Law, and Doctors in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited caſe, agreeing in every point with all that has been debated for the Purſuer. To the Second, That 1mo. It is <hi>ſimpliciter</hi> denyed, that the giving Obedience to the Lords decreet, when there is no remedie competent, for reclaiming againſt the ſame, can inferr a Homologation, as the Lords themſelves found in the caſe of <hi>Mrs. Dowglas,</hi> and the Children of <hi>Monſwal</hi> againſt the Duke of <hi>Queensberrie.</hi> 2do. That in this caſe of the Purſuer, it is utterly denyed there was any thing of a Legal ſentence, upon a lybel, or hearing of the Purſuer upon his intereſt, but allanerly a ſummar and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive act, or Ordinance of the Lords in purſuance of the Kings pleaſure, againſt which there was no Remedie by Reclaiming, without the hazard of being counted ſeditions,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180403:4"/>and puniſhed as an impugner of the Kings pleaſure, Which how dangerous, is left to your Lordſhips to judge. Eſpecially, when upon his owning of his intereſt, And plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the benefite of the Claime of Right, after This Happy Revolution, he is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with extraordinary matters, as is well known, And the ſaid very executive act, or Ordinance of the Lords, is one of the means of <hi>concuſſion,</hi> complained of; For had not the ſame followed on the Kings Letter, the Purſuer might have keeped his place; And therefore nothing done be the Purſuer in complyance with the Executive Ordinance, while that Government laſted, can in conſtruction of Law be underſtood any thing elſe, but the effects of the Aw that was upon him, why he durſt not aſſert his own Right, but either comply or outerly loſe all. To the 3d. That the ſame is an abſurd quible, for not only were all imaginable compulſitors that might turn the purſuer out of his place (The keeping, whereof was the only mean that did ſecure him againſt the 7000 Merks) already execute, and he actualy turned out, and an other inſtalled in his place; But there ſtill remained a farther and moſt vehement compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor againſt him, for taking the 7000 Merks, <hi>Viz.</hi> That otherwayes by inevitable neceſſity he behooved to loſe all; And the Law ſecuring him under ſuch a neceſſitous Juncture, That what ever he did for ſaving a part of his means, rather then to loſe all: His ſo ſaving to prevent his utter loſs, can never be conſtructed an act of deliberat and ſpontaneous renouncing the benefite of recovering what he injuriouſly loſt, but allenat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſaving of what for the time he could, and this likewayes is held as a principle by all Lawyers, that the party concuſſed from his Right and accepting of the mean price, and diſponing his intereſt, is never underſtood to Homologate the concuſſion or affent to the wrong done him: But allanarly to conſult his own intereſt, <hi>Quo minus perderet,</hi> and the ſame queſtion occurred in that caſe of the Lady <hi>Grayes,</hi> and all others of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion, wherein the partie laeſed, did both give Rights and take money, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thereof was alwayes reſtored againſt ſuch deeds, and whatever elſe they could have done under awful circumſtances, which debarred them from redreſs and remedie for the time. Upon which debate, the Commiſſion pronounced their interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitor in the Terms following, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>The Commiſſion of Parliament appointed for Fynes and Forfaulters are of opinion, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deed done by the purſuer during the power of the concuſſion cannot import an homologa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords ſentence, ſo farr as to debarr him from reſtitution, when the bazard is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: And therefore that the ſaid purſuer ought to be reponed to his Office of Clerk ſhip.</q>
               <p>The purſuet is able to inſtruct. That by continual perſecutions, impriſonments, and other miſeries which he was expoſed to in the late evil Government, even after he was caſt out of his Office, his loſſes multiplyed and did ariſe to a very conſiderable ſum, to the great detriment, &amp; almoſt ruine of his Familie, tho the preceeding part of his life had been a courſe of ſerving and ſuffering for the Royal Family &amp; his Country. All which did not diſcourage him from the little ſervices he was capable of &amp; had occaſion to perform ſince the late happy Revolution. Therefore he is moſt confident to obtain Juſtice, and to be reſtored to his office, which is his undoubted right by a Parliament that hath expreſt ſo great a ſenſe of the evils done in the late reigns, &amp; did patticularly by the claime of right, provide for reſtitution of the loſs of offices. Eſpecially ſeeing the grounds of Law and reaſon in his caſe, whereupon the Commiſſion proceeded are moſt clear &amp; convincing to every mans reaſon, yet for furder ſatisfaction &amp; conviction, the proper words in the Act 1621, and in the Kings Letter 1676, with the Depoſitions of the Witneſſes, and Quotations of Law, and Practices are hereto ſubjoyned.</p>
               <q>Follows the Clauſes of the Act of Sederunt <hi>1621,</hi> whereby it appears evidently, that the Eſtabliſhment of the Clerkships in three Offices, was only intended, and not the diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of two officiating Clerks in each Office, and that whatever may be pretended; Yet the private Intereſt of the then Clerks, was the only Cauſe and Occaſion of the Act.</q>
               <p>It is the expreſs will of the Lords, Likeas, they hereby declare that their Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and providing of the Proviſion given to two perſons admitted in ilkee an of the ſaids three Offices, tends allanarly to eſtabliſh the Right and Security of the indiviſible
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180403:4"/>Place and Office in the perſon of two provided. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Likeas it is declared, that it ſhall not be permitted to the Clerk Regiſter preſent, or his Succeſſors in time comming, to joyn any perſon with the Clerks ſerving in the ſaids three Offices, except by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Conſent, and at the deſire of the Principal Clerk ſerving for the time in the place; And no otherwayes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Follows the Clauſes of the Kings Letter, anent the Deference enjoyned to the proceedings of the Lords of Seſſion, and the Order for turning out the Clerks: <hi>Anno 1676.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>As we have truſted you with the preſervation of the Rights and Properties of our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So we will ſuffer none of our Subjects to reproach your procedure, much leſs thoſe who ſerve before you, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> And it is OUR Furder Pleaſure, that in all time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there be only three ordinary Clerks of Seſſion, beſidethe Clerk of the Bills, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Ancient Conſtitution, and that of the number that now ſerve, ye make choiſe of three that ſhall ſtill ſerve, and that ye modify ſuch ſatisfaction to be payed by thoſe that remain, to thoſe that are to go out, as ye ſhall find Juſt and Reaſonable.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Follows the Texts of Common Law, Opinions of Doctors, Decifions of forraign Courts, Pratiques, and Deciſions of the Lords of Seſſion, whereby it is demonſtratively evident, That any Tranſaction, Contract, or other Deed, that a Party has been induceed into, by the Aw and Dread of Perſons in Authority, is reduceable, And the party laeſed to be reſtored againſt the ſame, as being induced by Concuſſion, or Impreſſion, and that even in the Caſe of Dread and Fear of a Soveraign, or Kings Command.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And that while the Authority or Cauſe whence the Fear proceeded does laſt, no Deed</hi> medio tempore <hi>by the Party laeſed, can import a Homologation in the leaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And that the Party laeſed his very private reclaiming, and teſtifying of his diſſent is an Evidence of his being Over-Awed, and that he had not the freedom of his Election and Will.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p n="1">1mo. The whole Tittles in the <hi>digeſt:</hi> &amp; <hi>God: de vi &amp; metu,</hi> particulatly the <hi>Lex. ij. Cod. de his qui vi, &amp;c.</hi> whereof the words are, <hi>Si per Impreſſionem quis aliquem metuens in offieio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutum</hi> (id eſt, in authoritate conſtitutum) <hi>rei ſuae ſub venditienis titulo fecerit ceſſionem, quod Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum fuitreddatur;</hi> That is, if a perſon out of Dread of any in Authority ſell his Goods or Right, that the thing ſold, be forth with reſtored back to the Seller, &amp; according to which Law, <hi>Bachovius</hi> and the Doctors, Judge Reſtoration competent againſt the Impreſſion, and Fear Inferred by perſons, <hi>Qui ſunt in poteſtate Summa &amp; perpetua,</hi> as <hi>Brounman</hi> upon this Law cites them.</p>
               <p n="2">2do. <hi>Maſcardus deprob Concl.</hi> 1055. <hi>Num.</hi> 36. Holds it as a principle that a Subject is reſtorable againſt the Laeſion, ſuſtained by a Tranſaction entered into by Authority, or Command of a King, and his words are, <hi>Quod metus Regius propter quem facta fuit Renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatio ab Epiſcopo placentino de Epiſcopatu ejuſdem eivitatis non impedit, quo minus illa renunciatio retractari poſſit.</hi> And the ſame is held by <hi>Baldus</hi> in his 142 Counſel, whereof the words are, <hi>Compromiſſum dicitur permeium factum eo quod partes teneantur parere Domino,</hi> ſo that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Authority of a Soveraign, or Lord interveens the party laeſed thereby, is in Law alwayes reſtoreable againſt the ſamen.</p>
               <p n="3">3tio. <hi>Sinclar</hi> in his Collection of the Lords deſciſions in the year 1543, anent the caſe of the Earl of <hi>Mortouns</hi> action againſt Q: <hi>Mary</hi> for reducing the Reſignation and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Earldome, made in favours of King <hi>James</hi> the 5th her Father; The Lords ſuſtained the action againſt her ſummarly. And Albeit ſhe was Minor, and the reaſon rendred in the deciſion, <hi>Per expreſſum,</hi> is as follows, <hi>Viz.</hi> Becauſe it is provided by the act of the Lords of Council, lately made ſince the deceaſe of the King, that whoſomever complains, that they were hurt in their poſſeſſions, Land, Heretages, Goods, or gear, be the King <hi>Mediate vel immediate,</hi> that it ſhould be <hi>leiſum</hi> for them to call the Queens Advocat and Comptroler be an ſimple Bill without delay of Table or dyet, to hear them reſtored again to their poſſeſſion &amp; that becauſe it was heavily murmoured that the King oppreſt ſome of his Leidges in ſick ſort in his lifetime, and they now complain'd thereon; The Lords now for relief of their own conſcience, and <hi>Saule</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed the ſame, and therefore the Lords decerned, as ſaid is, <hi>April</hi> 12. 1543.</p>
               <p n="4">4to. <hi>Balfour</hi> obſerves out of the records of the Seſſion, that on the 14 <hi>April,</hi> the ſaid 1543 Year of GOD, in the caſe of the Lord <hi>Mortoun</hi> againſt the Q: and 14 <hi>Jully</hi> 1543.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180403:5"/>Laird <hi>Dundaſs, Contra Craighall. I: <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: C:</hi> 58<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The Lords found that if a man be but ſolicited by the King to make a diſpoſition or allienation of his goods and gear, the allienation ſo made is underſtood to be throw juſt Fear &amp; Dreadour and much more, if a man be threatened and impriſoned be the King, and therefore that any ſuch allienation or diſpoſition is Reduceable, Void and Null.</p>
               <p n="5">5to. <hi>Sinclar</hi> obſerves, That upon the 23 of <hi>April,</hi> in the ſaid year 1543, in a Red: at the Lord <hi>Yeaſters</hi> Inſtance, of a Sentence and Declaration of his Majeſties Pleaſure pronunced by the King himſelf, annent the Shirriffſhip of <hi>Peebles.</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed heritably to my Lord, whereby upon the Kings being diſpleaſed with my Lord, that two Thieves did eſcape out of Priſon in my Lords Brothers Lifetime, which was the Brothers fault only, and ſubmitting himſelf to the Kings Determination and Will, the King decerned him to tyne the Shirriffſhip, and to grant Infeftment of the ſame to the Lord <hi>Fleeming.</hi> All which is accordingly performed, and yet in the ſaid year 1543, and after the Kings deceaſe, the Lord <hi>Yeaſter</hi> having intended his Reduction as ſaid is, The Lords by their Sentence <hi>Definitive</hi> reduced the Declaration of the Kings will, and Infeſtment that followed thereupon, and that for the reaſon following in expreſs Terms, <hi>Viz:</hi> Becauſe the King <hi>exc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſerat arbitrium boni Viri in declarando ſuam voluntatem quia gravius punierat dictum Dominum quam de jure puniendus erat pro hoc delicto.</hi> Becauſe by no Law, Reaſon or Conſuetude, ought he to have tint his Heritage thereof, and ſo the King could not upon the ſubmitting the matter have taken my Lords Heritage from him, <hi>Quia quando quis ſe refert voluntati adverſarii ſui ille non poteſt de jure inique arbitrari, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra rationem, Quod ſi fecerit reducitur ejus voluntas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6to. The Lords of Seſſion upon 20 <hi>December</hi> 1671. Obſerved by the Lord <hi>Stairs</hi> in the caſe Betwixt <hi>Bramfoord</hi> and <hi>Callender,</hi> wherein <hi>Bramfoord</hi> ſeeking repetition of a Summ payed be him to <hi>Callender,</hi> which payment <hi>Callender</hi> alleadged that <hi>Bramfoord</hi> had acquieſced unto by entring to the poſſeſſion of the Eſtate of <hi>Bramfoord,</hi> which had been forfaulted, and to which the Government in the year 1647. Did reſtore him upon the expreſs condition, that he ſhould not quarrel the payment of the Summ that he was then craving repetition of, the Lords found <hi>Bramfoord</hi> no wayes bound to ſtand to the Terms or condition of the foreſaid reſtoration, and that his poſſeſſing his Eſtate, Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it in the Terms and qualifications of the ſaid condition imported nothing, whereof the reaſon is marked to have been, becauſe <hi>Bramfoord</hi> was <hi>Ex neceſſitate,</hi> to yeild to the power of the Government for the time, wherewith he was not able to contend.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That in the caſe of concuſſion, the partie Laeſed his private reclaiming and teſtifying the wrong done him to his own friends, is good ground whereupon to reſtore him againſt all deeds done by him, <hi>medio Tempore</hi> in referance thereto, is Recorded.</head>
               <p n="1">1mo. By <hi>Papone</hi> as expreſly decided by the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> on the 9th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1545, whoſe words are, <hi>Feu Monſieur le Chancelier Poyet, homme redouté, ſit Commandement á un convenu par ſes ſoeurs, de faire partage auec elles, &amp; leur laiſſer leur portion virile dans troin mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is: a peine de perdere ſa part en l'heredite dont eſtoit queſtion. Voyant ce frere la Grandeur de ce Commandment dont il ne pouuoit reclamer, ores que ſes foeurs euſſent quitte. Voyant auſſi L. intoler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able greiff que ce luy eſtoit, obeyt mais ce fut apres auoer proteſte a part de l'iniure qui luy eſtoit faicte, &amp; de tout faire irriter en temps de juſtice. Ce qu'il obtint depuis par Arreſt de Paris a moyen de ladicte preſtation, Le.</hi> 9 <hi>iour d' Aouſt,</hi> 1543. <hi>Papon Lib:</hi> 16: <hi>tit.</hi> 3 <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> 10. And it is proven that the Purſuer did reclaim both publickly and privat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p n="2">2do. The caſe is alſo obſerved to have been the ſame way decided by the Senat of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe,</hi> and it is ſo determined by the practice of <hi>Holland,</hi> as is notted by <hi>Chriſtinaeus</hi> in his Deciſions of the ſoveraign Courts of <hi>Holland,</hi> vol: 2 <hi>deciſ:</hi> 114. <hi>num.</hi> 5 wherein he cites the practice of the Senat of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p n="3">3tio. That Fear and Aw ariſing from Deeds, which of their own Nature may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Awfulneſs, needs no Proteſtation at all to be interpoſed, is held as a principle by all Lawyers. Yet the Purſuer did proteſt and contend as much as was poſſible againſt the Awful Authority with which he had to do, as is evident by the Depoſitions fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:180403:5"/>
               <head>Follows the Depoſitions of the Witneſſes, Proving that the Purſuer Reclaimed both in publick and private.</head>
               <head type="sub">In preſence of Sir <hi>John Hall,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Hamiltoun.</hi> In the Cauſe of Mr. <hi>Alexander Monro,</hi> againſt Mrs. <hi>John Mackenzie</hi> and <hi>James Juſtice.</hi>
               </head>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="deposition">
                           <salute>SIR </salute>
                           <p>
                              <hi>John Baird</hi> of <hi>Newbyth,</hi> one of the Senators of the Golledge of Juſtice, Aged Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and above Married, being ſolemnly ſworn, purged, and examined, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pones, That it being now ſo long a time ſince the Kings Letter, concerning the Clerks, was read, to the Lords of Seſſion, The deponent cannot be ſpecial as to all and every one of the Particulars mentioned in the Interrogators, but depones that he remembets very well that the Purſuer did alwayes reclaim and repine againſt the order of the Lords, for reducing the Clerks to Three; and particularly for voting the Purſuer out as one, according to the meaning of the Kings Letter; And that he did reclaim both the time of the reading of the Letter in preſence of the Lords, and thereafter: And par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly that the Purſuer reclaimed againſt the deponent himſelf, and would hardly ſpeak with him for two years thereafter, <hi>Cauſa ſcientiae;</hi> The deponent was preſent where the ſaid Letter was read, and ſaw and heard <hi>ut Supra.</hi> And this is the truth, as he ſhall anſwer to GOD,</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Sic ſubſcr bitur, John Baird, John Hall, William Hamiltoun.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="deposition">
                           <salute>Sir</salute>
                           <p>
                              <hi>John Lockbart</hi> of <hi>Caſtlebill,</hi> aged fiftie or thereabout, <hi>Solutus,</hi> being ſolemnly ſworn, examined, and purged, depones, that the deponent cannot be poſſitive as to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular circumſtances of the expreſſions mentioned in the Interrogators, But depones, that he heard Commiſſar <hi>Monro</hi> declare his diſſatisfaction to the deponent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Letter was read; And as he remembers uſed ſome expreſſions reclaiming againſt the Letter the time it was read in preſence of the Lords; and after he was turned out, remembers he has uſed words of very great reſentment, for his being turned out, and that the deponent never heard Mr. <hi>Monro</hi> ſpeak of that ſubject, without repining <hi>Cauſa ſcientiae;</hi> The deponent was one of the Lords of Seſſion, the time of reading the ſaid <hi>Letter,</hi> and this is the truth, as he ſhall anſwer to GOD,</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Sic ſubſcribitur John Lockhart, John Hall, William Hamiltoun.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="deposition">
                           <p>
                              <hi>Robert Hamiltoun</hi> of <hi>Preſmennan,</hi> one of the Senators of the Colldege of Juſtice, Aged ſixty eight years, married, being ſolemnly ſworn purged, and examined, depones; He cannot remember of all the particular circumſtances mentioned in the Interrogators, but that he remembers on the day the Letter was read; The purſuer reclaimed againſt the ſame, and ſaid that he had acquired his place from Sir <hi>Arebbald Primroſe</hi> Lord Regiſter, and he thought it ſtrange that he ſhould be diſquieted therein for though he wanted a place, he thought the King in Honour ſhould have provided him to a place in reguard of his great ſervices &amp; ſufferings for his Majeſtie both in <hi>England, Scotland, and Ireland,</hi> Depones, that the Letter being read, and after the Commiſſars reclaiming all the Clerks were put out to the outter houſe, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out calling any of them in, as the deponent heard, to intimat the ſentence to them that they were put out. And the next morning the Purſuer came to the deponents Chamber, and declared he would go in and poſſels his ſeat as Clerk of the Seſſion, ſince there was no intimation of the ſentence againſt him, and deſired the deponent might go with him, whereunto the deponent conſented &amp; went both towards the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament houſe, The length of the midle of the old Kirk, where Sir <hi>Patri<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>k Murray</hi> met them, who asked where the deponent, and the Purſuer were going, To which the Commiſſar anſwered, that he was going to keep poſſeſſion of his own ſeat as Clerk of the Seſſion, and the deponent did acknowledge he was going there alſo for the ſame purpoſe, whereupon Sir <hi>Patrick Murray</hi> by ſeveral arguments did diſwade them to go becauſe it would be ill taken, and would prejudge them, by which they were both perſwaded to go back with him, and further depones, that the deponent did often after that, hear the Purſuer reclaim againſt the ſaid ſentence <hi>Cauſa ſcientiae patet,</hi> and this is the Truth, as he ſhall anſwer to GOD,</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Sic ſubſcribetur Robert Hamiltoun, John Hall, William Hamiltoun.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="deposition">
                           <salute>Sir</salute>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Alexander Gibſon</hi> of <hi>Adeſton,</hi> one of the Clerks of Seſſion, aged fifty five years or thereby married, being ſolemnly ſworn, purged, and examined, depones, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Kings Letter for reducing the Clerks was read, Commiſſar <hi>Monro</hi> did make a Repreſentation to the Lords of his concern in that Matter, and deſired that they would take his Caſe to conſideration, before they proceeded on the matter, but what
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180403:6"/>were the Expreſſions or Arguments uſed to that purpoſe, The Deponent does not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, now after ſo long time, having taken no note or minute thereof at the time, nor does he remember what anſwer was given to what he ſpoke; But depones, That Commiſſar <hi>Monro</hi> did reclaim, and complained of his being removed from his place, as a great injurie done to him. And depones, That he never heard Commiſſar <hi>Monro</hi> ſpeak of his being turned out, but with gerat diſſatisfaction, and reſentment, <hi>cauſa ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae pates;</hi> And this is the Truth, as he ſhall anſwer to GOD,</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>ſic ſubſcribitur, Al: Gibſon, John Hall, Will: Hamilton.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="deposition">
                           <salute>Sir</salute>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Patrick Murray,</hi> Their Majeſties Receiver General, Aged about fifty years, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, being ſolemnly ſworn, purged, and examined, Depones, That he met with <hi>Preſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                                    <desc>••••</desc>
                                 </gap>an</hi> and Commiſſar <hi>Monro</hi> in the Old Kirk the next day, after they were put out, And he asked them, Where they were going? Who anſwered, That they were going to take their ſeats as Clerks of Seſſion; And that the Deponent uſed many arguments with them, to return back, and not go in; And that Commiſſar <hi>Monro</hi> was more carneſt to go forward then <hi>Preſmennan:</hi> But the Deponent having uſed many perſwaſive Arguments with them, to return for fear of greater prejudice to them, they were at laſt enduced to return: And the Deponent went with them, to the houſe now called <hi>Alexander Crombies,</hi> and took his Morning drink with them. And farther, Depones, That he never heard Commiſſar <hi>Monro</hi> ſpeak of his being turned out, but with great reſentment, and complaint, as a great Oppreſſion done to him, but remembers nothing of his giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a ſupplication to the King thereanent at <hi>Windz<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>r, Anno</hi> 1679. <hi>cauſa ſcientiae patet,</hi> And this is the Truth, As he ſhall Anſwer to GOD;</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>ſie ſubſcribitur Patrick Murray, John Hall, Will. Hamilton.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Next Point is.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That in the caſe of Concuſſion, Fear or Aw ariſing from any perſon in Authoritie, nothing done by the partie Laeſed, during the continuance of the ſaid Awfull Authoritie, can import any Homologation, nor yet hinder the partie Laeſed from being reſtored, it poſitively beld.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1mo. By <hi>Maſcard ubi ſupra <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>luſ:</hi> 1055. <hi>num:</hi> 34: <hi>&amp;</hi> 36: where his words are, <hi>Quando metus femel illatus fuiſſes ſemper perſeverare praeſumitur ideoque, quod metu follum eſt ab initio, &amp; ſi poſteaconſtrmatum futrit, nullas vires tamen babet, quia praeſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>itur metu confirmatuin</hi> And for this, cites the foreſaid <hi>Lex</hi> II: <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d: ſi per impreſſionem.</hi> And the Example he adduces is in the words following, <hi>Quod metus regius propter quem facta fuit renunciatio; ab Epiſcopo pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centino de Epiſcopatis ejuſdem civitatis pro Epiſcopatu Aſtenſi, Non ſit purgatus ex eo quod Geſſit ſe per quinquennium pro Epiſcopo Aſtenſi;</hi> And the reaſon rendred by him is, <hi>quia omnia quae facta ſunt, poſt renuntiationem metiouloſam facta fuerunt durante eodem timore regiae Majeſtatis quae non impediunt quo minus illa renunciatio, Retractari poſſit;</hi> and for this aduces the authoritie of <hi>Bartole, Abbas, Alexander,</hi> Cornel: <hi>Barbat: Decius: Paris: Boer:</hi> and twenty more.</p>
               <p n="2">2do. The foreſaid <hi>Balfour</hi> obſerves that upon the 15 of <hi>April</hi> 1543, in the ſaid caſe L: <hi>Mortcun contra</hi> the Queen, The Lords did find in the expreſs words following, <hi>Viz.</hi> That the Dread and Fear once occaſioned by the King continued, and endured till his Highneſs deceaſe, who was the cauſe thereof, So that dureing his lifetime, the maker of the ſaid infeftment or diſpoſition durſt not Purſue for reduction thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3tio. That the Lords of Seſſion in the foreſaid Caſe of <hi>Bramfoord Anno</hi> 1671, did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly find, that albeit the forefaulture of <hi>Bramfords</hi> Eſtate was taken off, and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate reſtored to him upon the condition that he ſhould not Quarrel the Summs uplift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Callender:</hi> And albeit <hi>Bramfoord</hi> did accordingly poſſeſs his Eſtate, to which he was reſtored upon the ſaid expreſs Condition: Yet the Lords found that his ſo poſſeſſing could not import an homologation of the Condition, or debarr <hi>Bramfoord</hi> from craving Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Money, &amp; the Reaſon adduced is, becauſe Homologation muſt import a free conſent, which the Lords found <hi>Bramfoord</hi> had not the freedome of under the then Government, but behooved to poſſeſs his Eſtate under what ever Condition or Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation they pleaſed, till the revolution did come about, whereupon the alleadgeance of his Homologation was repelled.</p>
               <p n="4">4to. The Lords upon the 27 of <hi>June</hi> 1632, As <hi>Durie</hi> obſerves in the Caſe betwixt <hi>Caſſie</hi> and <hi>Fleyming,</hi> did repone a Wiſe againſt her conſenting with her Husband to the alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of her Joynture Lands, in reſpect that her Husband had over awed her thereto
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180403:6"/>ſometime before, and was ſtill on Life the time of her Conſent, and the <hi>ratio decidendi</hi> expreſly marked by <hi>Durie</hi> in the very Terms of Law, and Language of the Doctors is, <hi>Quia durante &amp; ſubſiſtente eadem cauſa metus, nunequam etiam cum intervallo metus purgatur</hi> So that during the Husbands Liftime, the Wife was alwayes found to be under Aw, albeit the time of her Conſenting, ſhe teſtified nothing of it. Likeas in the ſame Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Lords found the Wifes Action of Reduction, <hi>ex capite metas,</hi> competent againſt a Wod-ſetter of the Liferented Lands, who had no acceſſion to the Fear, becauſe <hi>Durit</hi> makes the Action <hi>ex metu,</hi> to have been ſuſtained as in <hi>rem ſcripta,</hi> and competent <hi>contra quemcunque poſſeſſorem,</hi> as alſo that in the ſame Deciſion, the Lords found that neither the Wifes conſenting, nor yet her receiving the Price of her Joyntur Lands, immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly her ſelf could be any Acts of Homologation, becauſe ſhe had not freedome of Will during her Husbands Life, and that it is a principle, that <hi>velle non creditur qui obſequitur imperio patris vel domini.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5to. That the Lords upon the 21 of <hi>July</hi> the ſaid year, (as <hi>Durie</hi> aiſo obſerves in the paralele Caſe betwixt <hi>Hamiltoun contra</hi> 
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> ) declare they will decide that Caſe of <hi>Hamiltouns,</hi> as they did in the foreſaid Caſe of <hi>Caſſie contra Fleming:</hi> So that the practice of <hi>Scotland,</hi> has eſtabliſhed it as a principle, that <hi>durante cauſa metus nunquam purgatur nutus;</hi> And therefore that what is <hi>medio tempore</hi> done by the party Laeſed, can never import an Homologation of the Tranſaction <hi>Meticuloſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6to. In the late Caſe of Concuſſion at the Lady <hi>Grays</hi> Inſtance, againſt the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> it is very well known, that after <hi>Lauderdale</hi> was in Poſſeſſion of the Ladys Eſtate, by Concuſſion ſhe did receive either 20 or 30000 Merks as the price of her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and thereupon actually diſponed the ſame to <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> nevertheleſs the Lords did in Juſtice repone her againſt the ſaid Tranſaction, as being the effect of invincible neceſſity upon her for the time, to accept of ſome thing rather than loſs all. So that a <hi>paritate rationis; Hayſtoun</hi> being actually inſtalled in the Purſuers Office, out of which he was not able to remove him for the time: What in the world remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him, but (as the Lady <hi>Gray</hi> did) to take the mean thing that was wrongouſly modifyed by the Lords, and renounce for the time rather then to loſs all.</p>
               <p n="7">7mo. The poſitive opinion of Lawyers and Doctors, as <hi>Bartol:</hi> upon the <hi>Lex:</hi> 4. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> De his que vi &amp; metu.</hi> States it in the caſe of one that is thorow Fear &amp; Terror induced to ſell, and afterwards receives the price, is That his ſo receiving the price does never import a Homologation of the tranſaction <hi>metiouloſa:</hi> If the ſeller for the time could do no better. And if any other conſideration can be fixed upon for the Seller his taking the price, Then that of homologation, his words are, <hi>Quod receptio pretii Spontanea non inducit approbationem contractus imo enim recipia pratium ut ſit mihi majus <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>autum, Quia tant<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> minus babeo perdere unde poteſt eſſe alia ratio quam apprebationis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8vo. And laſtly to Summ up all The late Act of Parliament reſtoring againſt Fynes and Forfaulturs in the late Reigns, and reponing againſt all tranſactions thereanent, is upon no other ground, but that the parties Laeſed and tranſacting, were dureing the whole time of the late government under Aw; So that they had no freedome of election, or choice, But were under Conſtraint and Neceſſity to undergo that which ſeemed to be the leaſt ill.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:180403:7"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
